Guide to the Thomas Mann Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Thomas Mann. Writings, 1926-45; Series I; 5; (12 boxes)
  - 77. [Rede ueber Lessing] LESSING Autograph manuscript with underscoring; 16 leaves numbered 1-13 (the last 3 leaves are unnumbered) The inscription "Vorarbeiten zum Lessing-Essay" appears on the back of the last leaf in TM's hand (Box 11, Folder 182)
  - 78. REDE UeBER NIETZSCHE Autograph manuscript with corrections and deletions, dated: 3 xi. 24, 6 numbered leaves (Box 11, Folder 183)
  - 79. [Rede zum 70. Geburtstag von Heinrich Mann] LIEBER HEINRICH, MEINE DAMEN UND HERREN Typescript (original) with corrections by TM; 6 numbered leaves (Box 11, Folder 184)
  - 80. SCHOPENHAUER Mimeographed typescript; 33 leaves numbered 1-32 (15a inserted) (Box 11, Folder 185)
  - See also: Essays of Three Decades, Box 6, folder 77
  - 81. "SI LE GRAIN NE MEURT-" Autograph manuscript with corrections and deletions, dated: 14. x. 29; 12 numbered leaves (Box 11, Folder 186)
  - 82. [Speech at a Dinner for Ambassador Alvarez del Vayo] Typescript (original) with corrections by HLP, 4 leaves; a small portion of this text is taken from the essay "Spanien" (Box 11, Folder 187)
  - 83. DER TAG DES BUCHES Autograph manuscript with corrections and deletions, dated: Muenchen, Februar 1929; 4 numbered leaves (Box 11, Folder 188)
  - 84. [Thomas Masaryk] ZU MASARYKS GEDAeCHTNIS Typescript (carbon) with corrections and title in TM's hand; 5 numbered leaves [English translation by HLP] IN MEMORY OF MASARYK Typescript (original) with corrections; 6 leaves (Box 11, Folder 189)
  - 85. [Tischrede auf dem Federal Union Dinner] DINNER SPEECH FOR FEDERAL UNION, BEVERLY HILLS HOTEL Typescript (original) with corrections, deletions, and the title in TM's hand; 7 numbered leaves (Box 11, Folder 190)
  - 86. [Tod in Venedig] BLATT AUS DEN NOTIZEN ZUM "TOD IN VENEDIG" Autograph manuscript, 1 leaf; with typed English translation, 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 191)
  - 87. UeBER DEN FILM Autograph manuscript with corrections, dated: Muenchen, den 23. III. 28; 4 leaves (5 pages of text) (Box 11, Folder 192)
  - 88. [Ueber die Ehe] DIE EHE IM UeBERGANG Autograph manuscript with corrections and deletions; 22 numbered leaves (Box 11, Folder 193)
  - 89. UEBER GOETHES "FAUST" Typescript (original) with a few corrections by TM, dated: Kuesnacht, New York und Princeton, Sept.-Okt. 1938; 45 numbered leaves [English translation by HLP] GOETHE'S FAUST Typescript (original) with corrections by TM and HLP, dated: Kuesnacht, New York and Princeton, September-October 1938; 61 leaves numbered 1-60 (55a inserted) (Box 11, Folder 194-195)
  - See also: Essays of Three Decades, Box 6, folder 77
  - 90. UEBER "THE HOLY SINNER" Typescript (original) with corrections by TM; 5 numbered leaves [English translation by HLP] ABOUT "THE HOLY SINNER" Typescript (original) with corrections by HLP; 5 numbered leaves (Box 11, Folder 196)
  - 91. [Ueber Unordnung und fruehes Leid] SELBSTANZEIGE Autograph manuscript with corrections, signed; 3 leaves (Box 11, Folder 197)
  - 92. DIE VERTAUSCHTEN KOePFE Typescript (carbon) with corrections by TM and a few marginal notes and queries by HLP; 111 leaves numbered 1-112 (44 omitted in numbering) (Box 11, Folder 198)
  - 93. [Die vertauschten Koepfe. English translation by HLP. The Transposed Heads] Typescript (carbon) with corrections by HLP; 91 numbered leaves, with a typed list headed "Suggested titles," 1 leaf, and a short list of queries keyed to the German typescript, in an unknown hand, 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 199)
  - 94. VOM GEIST DER MEDIZIN Autograph manuscript with corrections, signed and dated; Muenchen den 24. VI. 25; 7 numbered leaves (Box 11, Folder 200)
  - 95. [Vor dem Amerikanischen Rescue Comittee] MEINE DAMEN UND HERREN Typescript (original) with a few corrections by TM; 8 numbered leaves (Box 11, Folder 201)
  - 96. VORWORT [In: Hermann Ungars "Colberts Reise und andere Erzaehlungen"] Autograph manuscript with corrections and deletions, signed and dated: Nidden, Kur. Nehrung, August, 1930; 7 numbered leaves (Box 11, Folder 202)
  - 97. [Vorwort zu Joseph Conrads Roman "Der Geheimagent"] EINLEITUNG Autograph manuscript with corrections and deletions, signed and dated: Forte dei Marmi, August 1926; 16 numbered leaves (leaf 5 in 2 sections) (Box 11, Folder 203)
  - 98. [Vorwort zu Masereels "Stundenbuch"] ZUM MASEREEL-AUFSATZ Autograph manuscript notes with underscoring; 6 leaves (Box 11, Folder 204)
  - 99. [War and Democracy] Typescript (part original, part carbon) with corrections in an unknown hand; 20 numbered leaves Galley proofs, corrected by a proofreader; 7 sheets and a title page Another set of galley proofs, corrected by TM and a proofreader; 7 sheets and a title page Page proofs, corrected by a proofreader; 5 preliminary leaves, 25 pages Printed invitation to this lecture, held on 3 October 1940, with 2 copies of JWA's (printed) biographical sketch of TM laid in (Box 11, Folder 205)
  - 100. [The War and the Future. German original] DER KRIEG UND DIE ZUKUNFT Typescript (original) with a few corrections by TM; 20 numbered leaves. Portions of the text are already in English in this typescript [Fragments from an English translation by HLP] Typescript (original) with notes by HLP; 3 nonconsecutive leaves (Box 11, Folder 206)
  - 101. [Was wir verlangen muessen] GEGEN DIE FALSCHE REVOLUTION I [-II] Typescript (carbon) with titles in TM's hand; 6 leaves numbered 1-4 (section I) and 1-2 (section II) (Box 11, Folder 207)
  - 102. [What I believe] Typescript (original) with corrections by HLP; 9 leaves Typescript (carbon) of the corrected version; 10 leaves (Box 11, Folder 208)
  - 103. [Der Zauberberg] AUSGESCHIEDENE UND UMGEARBEITETE SEITEN AUS DEM "ZAUBERBERG" Autograph manuscript with many corrections, insertions and deletions; 71 nonconsecutive leaves numbered 7-40, 42, zu S. 42, 59-69, 107-108, 133-135, 139, 149-151, 558-572 Typed transcript, introduction, and editorial apparatus by James F. White; 198 pages. Published as vol. 4 of Thomas Mann Studien in 1980. (Box 12, Folder 209-213)
  - 104. ZUM 60. GEBURTSTAG RICHARDA HUCHS Autograph manuscript with corrections; 6 numbered leaves (Box 12, Folder 214)
  - 105. [Zur Gruendung einer Dokumentensammlung] REDE BEI DER EROeFFNUNG DER T. M. LIBRARY AN DER YALE-UNIVERSITAeT Autograph manuscript with corrections, dated: 17. XII. 37; 13 numbered leaves, with typed transcript of the opening paragraphs; 1 leaf, with carbon copy Typescript (original) with underscoring and a few corrections in TM's hand; 11 numbered leaves Another typed copy; 11 numbered leaves (Box 12, Folder 215-216)
  - 105a. ZUR JÜDISCHEN FRAGE Printed letter to E. Frisch, intended for publication in the Neuer Merkur in the early 1920s; 9 numbered leaves, with typescript notes by an unidentified writer and an accompanying typescript statement concerning the letter, signed by Alfred Vagts, 1938 Nov 7. (Box 12, Folder 216a)
  - 106. [Two unidentified, separate pages, in English] Typescript (original) with corrections by HLP; 1 leaf "It moves me deeply to be privileged to speak to the citizens of England.. ." Written during World War II Typescript (carbon) with corrections by HLP; 1 leaf numbered 42; from a political essay (Box 12, Folder 217)
- Letters by Thomas Mann, 1894-55; Series II; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  - Angell, Joseph Warner, 1935-51 (Box 13, Folder 218-219)
  - 45 TLS, 1 ALS
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also: Angell, Joseph Warner, Box 16, folder 277
  - Auerbach, Erich, 1949-51 (Box 13, Folder 220)
  - 1 TLS, 2 ALS (Negative photostats only)
  - Cunz, Dieter, 1944 (Box 13, Folder 221)
  - 1 ALS (Positive photostat only)
  - Dehmel, Ida, 1909-14 (Box 13, Folder 222)
  - 2 ALS, 1 APCS (Positive photostats only; originals in Hamb. Staats-u. Universitaets-Bibliothek) Dehmel, Richard, 1894-1920
  - 11 ALS, 2 APCS, 1 tel. (Positive photostats only; originals in Hamb. Staats-u. Universitaets-Bibliothek)
  - Dial Press, 1948 (Box 13, Folder 223)
  - 1 ALS
  - Dunham, T. Chadbourne, 1940-41 (Box 13, Folder 224)
  - 2 TLS
  - Eckstein, Alice Raphael, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 225)
  - 1 TLS
  - Heuschele, Otto See: Pulver
  - Hirschbach, Frank Donald, 1950-54 (Box 13, Folder 226)
  - 3 ALS
  - Hoppe, Chi Chi, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 227)
  - 1 TLS
  - Jaffe, Fritz, 1953 (Box 13, Folder 228)
  - 1 TL (Typed copy only)
  - Jamieson, Burton Lloyd, 1930 (Box 13, Folder 229)
  - 1 ACS
  - Jonas, Klaus W., 1949-54 (Box 13, Folder 230)
  - 5 TLS, 6 ALS (Negative photostats only)
  - Knopf, Alfred A., 1927-53 (Box 13, Folder 231)
  - 1 TLS, 1 TL (TL carbon copy, filed with TMs letter to AEM, 1953 Feb 8)
  - Lewis, Wilmarth Sheldon, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 232)
  - 1 TLS
  - Lowe, Helen Tracy (Porter), 1924-1954, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 233-234)
  - 39 ALS, 86 TLS, 1 APCS, 2 TL, 2 AC, 1 ANS
  - Meyer, Agnes Elizabeth (Ernst), 1937-55 (Box 13, Folder 235-238)
  - 28 TLS, 273 ALS, 13 tel, 7 APCS, 3 ACS
  - Meyer, Agnes Elizabeth (Ernst) (cont.), 1937-55 (Box 14, Folder 239-246)
  - Meyer, Agnes Elizabeth (Ernst) (cont.), 1937-55 (Box 15, Folder 247-256)
  - Paterson, Mrs. George T., 1940 (Box 15, Folder 257)
  - 1 TLS
  - Pauker, John, 1940 (Box 15, Folder 258)
  - 1 ALS
  - PM, Editor, 1945 (Box 15, Folder 259)
  - 1 TL (Two carbon copies)
  - Powys, Llewelyn, 1927 (Box 15, Folder 260)
  - 1 TLS
  - Pratt, George C, 1933 (Box 15, Folder 261)
  - 1 TLS
  - Preston, John Hyde, 1938 (Box 15, Folder 262)
  - 1 TLS
  - [Pulver, Max] Heuschele, Otto, 1927 (Box 15, Folder 263)
  - 1 ALS
  - Rosenau, Ruth H., 1942 (Box 15, Folder 264)
  - 1 TLS
  - Schatzki, Walter 1 ALS With a file of material relating to the 50 copy limited German language edition of Doktor Faustus produced by Schatzki to conform with American copyright law. Includes letters, clippings, a contract between Bermann-Fischer and Schatzki, and financial statements. (Box 15, Folder 265)
  - Schwering, Prof. [i.e. Julius Schwering? 1863-1941?], 1907 (Box 15, Folder 266)
  - 1 APCS
  - Severing & Goldmann, firm, Munich, 1932 (Box 15, Folder 267)
  - 1 APCS (Negative photostat only)
  - Skuhra, Herr (Viennese publisher?), 1924 (Box 15, Folder 268)
  - 1 ALS
  - Thirlwall, John Connop, 1951 (Box 15, Folder 269)
  - 1 ALS, 1 TLS
  - Weigand, Hermann John, 1927-52 (Box 15, Folder 270-271)
  - 7 TLS, 6 ALS, 1 ACS, 1 APCS
  - White, James Fellows, 1939-50 (Box 15, Folder 272)
  - 2 TLS
  - Whitehall [Whitehall?], Virginia N., 1939 (Box 15, Folder 273)
  - 2 TLS
  - Yale University Library, 1940-52 (Box 15, Folder 274-275)
  - 14 TLS
  - Yourcenar, Marguerite, 1955 (Box 15, Folder 276)
  - 1 ALS (Photocopy only, with typed translation and draft of a reply)
- Letters by Katia Mann, 1909-55; Series III; 0.5; (.5 box)
  - Angell, Joseph Warner (Box 16, Folder 277)
  - 7 TLS, 4 ALS
  - Dehmel, Ida, 1909 (Box 16, Folder 278)
  - 1 ALS (Positive photostat only)
  - Jonas, Klaus W., 1954-55 (Box 16, Folder 279)
  - 2 TLS (Negative photostats only)
  - Lowe, Helen Tracy (Porter), 1928-52 (Box 16, Folder 280)
  - 24 TLS, 2 ALS, 2 APCS
  - Meyer, Agnes Elizabeth (Ernst), 1937-43 (Box 16, Folder 281)
  - 11 TLS, 9 ALS
- Letters to Thomas Mann, 1937-54; Series IV; 0.5; (.5 box)
  - Evans, Luther H
    See: AEM to TM, 1950 Mar 23
  - Hoppe, Chi Chi, 1938 (Box 16, Folder 282)
  - 1 TL, 1 TLS
  - Library of Congress
    See: Luther H. Evans, Box 16, folder 282
    See: Archibald MacLeish, Box 16, folder 284
    See: David C. Mearns, Box 16, folder 285
  - Lowe, Helen Tracy (Porter), 1937-52 (Box 16, Folder 283)
  - 6 TL, 1 ALS, 1 AL
  - MacLeish, Archibald, 1941 (Box 16, Folder 284)
  - 1 TL
  - Mearns, David C., 1948 (Box 16, Folder 285)
  - 1 TL
  - Meyer, Agnes Elizabeth (Ernst), 1937-54 (Box 16, Folder 286a-286f)
  - 58 ALS, 2 TL, 4 AL, 1 AN
  - Weigand, Hermann John, 1937 (Box 16, Folder 287)
  - 1 TL
  - White, James Fellows, 1950 (Box 16, Folder 288)
  - 1 TL
  - Yale University Library, 1941-52 (Box 16, Folder 289)
  - 6 TL
- MISCELLANEOUS LETTERS, 1931-45; Series V; 0.5; (.5 box)
  - Clapp, Verner M., 1942 (Box 17, Folder 290)
  - TLS to AEM
  - Dewey, John, 1938 (Box 17, Folder 291)
  - ALS to AEM
  - Library of Congress
    See: Verner Clapp, Box 17, folder 290
    See: Archibald MacLeish, Box 17, folder 293
    See: Wade Rabbitt, Box 17, folder 300
  - Lowe, Helen Tracy (Porter), 1938 (Box 17, Folder 292)
  - TLS to AEM TL to Henry Hatfield, 1951 (Draft)
  - MacLeish, Archibald, 1941-42 (Box 17, Folder 293)
  - 2 TLS to AEM
  - McHale, Kathryn, 1931 (Box 17, Folder 294)
  - TLS to AEM
  - Mann, Erika, 1937-38 (Box 17, Folder 295)
  - 5 TLS to AEM
  - Mann, Golo, 1943-44 (Box 17, Folder 296)
  - 3 TLS to AEM
  - Mann, Klaus, 1939 (Box 17, Folder 297)
  - TLS to AE
  - Mott, Frank Luther, 1945 (Box 17, Folder 298)
  - TL to AEM
  - Panofsky, Erwin, 1940 (Box 17, Folder 299)
  - TL to Alfred E. Knopf
  - Rabbitt, Wade E., 1942 (Box 17, Folder 300)
  - TLS to AEM
  - Venable, Vernon, 1938 (Box 17, Folder 301)
  - TLS to AEM
- Manuscripts about Thomas Mann, 1926-45; Series VI; 0.5; (.5 box)
  - Angell, Joseph Warner TEXT OF PREFACE TO THOMAS-MANN-STUDIEN, PROFESSOR JAMES F. WHITE'S EDITION OF THE ZAUBERBERG MANUSCRIPT PAGES Typescript (photocopy); 1 leaf, 16 numbered leaves, with manuscript corrections and suggestions by Marjorie G. Wynne and in another hand (Box 17, Folder 302)
  - Gauss, Christian Frederick MEETING IN HONOR OF THOMAS MANN'S SEVENTIETH BIRTHDAY, NEW YORK CITY - JUNE 9, 1945 Typescript (original); 5 numbered leaves (Box 17, Folder 303)
  - Jacob, Gerhard [Das Werk Thomas Manns; Bibliographie] GEDRUCKT IM JANUAR 1926 IN EINER AUFLAGE VON 400 EXEMPLAREN VOM BIBLIOGRAPHISCHEN INSTITUT IN LEIPZIG Typescript (carbon); 3 leaves, 39 numbered leaves. Published by S. Fischer in 1926 (Box 17, Folder 304)
  - Jonas, Klaus W FIFTY YEARS OF THOMAS MANN STUDIES [Outline of proposed bibliography] Typescript (carbon); 2 leaves (Box 17, Folder 305)
  - Lowe, Helen Tracy (Porter) SYNOPSIS [of TM's novel Doktor Faustus] Typescript (original); 5 leaves with added cover (Box 17, Folder 306)
  - Lowe, Helen Tracy (Porter) THE THOUGHT THE WORD AND THE DEED [For TM's 70th birthday] Typescript (original), signed; 2 numbered leaves (Box 17, Folder 307)
  - Meyer, Agnes Elizabeth (Ernst) [Autograph notes, chiefly on Doktor Faustus] 50 leaves (Box 17, Folder 308)
  - Meyer, Agnes Elizabeth (Ernst) [Autograph notes, removed from TM's Rede und Antwort]; 26 leaves (Box 17, Folder 309)
  - Meyer, Agnes Elizabeth (Ernst) BIRTHDAY SALUTATION TO THOMAS MANN [for TM's 65th birthday] Typescript (original); 2 leaves, with envelope addressed to TM in AEM's hand (Box 17, Folder 310)
  - Meyer, Agnes Elizabeth (Ernst) GOLDNE TRAeUME [Poem for TM] Autograph manuscript, dated April 2, 1942; 2 copies (Box 17, Folder 311)
  - Meyer, Agnes Elizabeth (Ernst) LUeBECK AS A FORM OF LIFE [Essay about TM] Typescript (original) with manuscript corrections by AEM; 27 numbered leaves, with 2 leaves of autograph notes inserted Typescript (carbon) with manuscript corrections by AEM; 27 numbered leaves, with 9 leaves of autograph notes inserted (Box 17, Folder 312)
  - Meyer, Agnes Elizabeth (Ernst) NOTES ON DR. FAUST. DURING VISIT OCT 12-15 - '43 Autograph manuscript; 2 numbered leaves (Box 17, Folder 313)
  - Meyer, Agnes Elizabeth (Ernst) SCHOPENHAUER ESSAY. T. MANN. FORDERUNG DES TAGES. LEIDEN U GROeSSE DER M WAGNER [On various works by TM] Autograph notes; 91 leaves of text in a bound notebook, with 4 leaves of autograph notes laid in (Box 17, Folder 314)
  - Meyer, Agnes Elizabeth (Ernst) SWISS PAPER ON FAUSTUS Autograph notes; 6 leaves (Box 17, Folder 315)
- Special Files, 1925-90; Series VII; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  1. Luebeck
  - a. 5 pamphlets about the city, 1 picture postcard (Box 18, Folder 316)
    and 2 prints
  - b. 2 photographs of the "Buddenbrooks" house, before (Box 18, Folder 317)
    and after it was bombed
  - c. 1 reproduction of an l8th-century view of the (Box 18, Folder 318)
    central square
  - 2. Photographs of Thomas Mann
  - a. By Steichen (1934) (Box 18, Folder 319)
    - b. By Florence Homolka (TM in a white jacket and bow tie, holding a cigarette) (Box 18, Folder 320)
    - c. TM writing at a table in a white shirt, no tie, cigarette (Box 18, Folder 321)
    - d. With KM at Yale in 1950. 4 prints (8x10"), one signed by TM and dedicated to David H. Clift (Box 18, Folder 322)
    - e. TM seated at a microphone, water in the background
      See: Oversize, Portfolio. folder 350
    - f. By Lotte Jacobi, signed by her
    - f2. Obituary of Lotte Jacobi, New York Times, 1990 May 9 (Box 18, Folder 323)
  - 3. Vance, Esther
    - Portrait of TM, 1940, oil on canvas, 25.5" x 32"
      See: Oversize, Art, folder 351
    - Clippings of obituary, New York Times and New Haven Register, 1983 Nov (Box 18, Folder 324)
  - Empty folder (Box 18, Folder 325)
  - 4. Die Familie Mann Family tree for years 1399-1949 (Box 18, Folder 326)
  - 5. Joseph in Egypt Drawings and proof for the plate and wrapper of the American edition, 6 items
    See: Oversize, Portfolio. folder 352
  - 6. Transcriptions of selected autograph manuscripts from the Yale collection, 52 leaves, typed and in an unknown hand (Box 18, Folder 327)
  - 7. Clippings by and about TM, 1928-52 (Box 18, Folder 328)
  - 8. Clippings about TM's lectures, public appearances, interview, and honors, 1926-53 (Box 18, Folder 329)
  - 9. Clippings containing general or slight accounts of TM and his works, 1925-52 (Box 18, Folder 330)
  - 10. Reviews of Doktor Faustus: clippings, 1948-49 (Box 18, Folder 331)
  - 11. Reviews of TM's essays: clippings, 1929-47 (Box 18, Folder 332)
  - 12. Reviews of Joseph und seine Brueder: clippings, 1934-48 (Box 18, Folder 333)
  - 13. Reviews of Lotte in Weimar: clippings, 1939-40 (Box 18, Folder 334)
  - 14. Reviews of Die vertauschten Koepfe: clippings, 1941 (Box 18, Folder 335)
  - 15. Reviews of Der Zauberberg: clippings, 1927 (Box 18, Folder 336)
  - 16. Reviews of other works by TM: clippings, 1927 (Box 18, Folder 337)
  - 17. Clippings of articles by and about HLP, 1927-49 (Box 18, Folder 338)
  - 18. Unidentified and fragmentary clippings (Box 18, Folder 339)
  - 19. Newspaper reviews of books about TM (Box 18, Folder 340)
  - 20. Recent clippings about TM (Box 18, Folder 341)
  - 20w. Clippings about TM compiled by James F. White (Box 19, Folder 342-342)
  - 21. Offprints of scholarly articles about TM (Box 19, Folder 344-345)
  - 22. Programs and other material relating to TM's public appearances and TM celebrations. Publishers' prospectuses about TM books. (Box 20, Folder 346a-346c)
  - 23. Enigmas a. ALS to Sehr geehrte gnaedige Frau, 1935 Sept 10, Washington, not in TM's hand; found among AEM's letters b. Printed page entitled Heinrich Heine, der "Gute." Von Paul Thomas (Box 20, Folder 347)
  - 24. Accession slips and lists (Box 20, Folder 348)
  - 25. Printed material relating to the Thomas-Mann-Archiv and the Thomas-Mann-Gesellschaft in Zuerich (Box 20, Folder 349)
- Oversize Items, 1940, n.d.; 2 portfolios and one framed portrait
  - Series VII. Special Files
    2. Photographs of Thomas Mann
    - e. TM seated at a microphone, water in the background f. By Lotte Jacobi, signed by her (Box Port, folder 350)
    - 3. Vance, Esther Portrait of TM, 1940, oil on canvas, 25.5" x 32" (Box Art, Folder 351)
    - 5. Joseph in Egypt Drawings and proof for the plate and wrapper of the American edition, 6 items (Box Port, folder 352)